<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spirit of Quakerism and the danger of their divine revelation in a faithful narrative of their malicious persecution of Henry Winder and his wife as murtherers at the publick assize at Carlisle / by Henry Winder.</title>
            <author>Winder, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66618</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2975</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31020</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11766367</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11766367</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48750</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66618)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48750)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1493:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spirit of Quakerism and the danger of their divine revelation in a faithful narrative of their malicious persecution of Henry Winder and his wife as murtherers at the publick assize at Carlisle / by Henry Winder.</title>
                  <author>Winder, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Harris ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages tightly bound with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Errata on p. [8]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  England.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48750:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Spirit of Quakeriſm,</hi> And the Danger of their Divine Revelation LAID OPEN: In a faithful Narrative of their malicious Proſecution of <hi>Henry Winden,</hi> and his Wife, as Murtherers, at the Publick Aſſize at <hi>Carliſle.</hi> By <hi>Henry Winder.</hi> WITH Suitable Reflections on the ſaid <hi>Narrative:</hi> Containing ſeveral other Inſtances of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Revelations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 7.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Beware of falſe Prophets which come unto you in ſheeps cloathing, but inwardly they are raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wolves.</p> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>v. 16.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>Ye ſhall know them by their fruits.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh. 4.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Beloved, believe not every Spirit, but try the Spirits whether they are of God.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Tantaene animis coeleſtibus Irae!</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Harris</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> in <hi>Little Britain,</hi> 1696. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:48750:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48750:2"/>
            <head>The AUTHOR's PREFACE.</head>
            <p>BEing deſired by Perſons of Worth and Eminence to give a publick account of the doleful and unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel'd Conflict I had with the Quakers, which was publickly acted, and yet ſo variouſly reported, that 'twas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſable for thoſe living at a diſtance to know the Truth; leſt I aſſent unto their importunity, and herein give a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Relation of the moſt material Paſſages: It's true, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g they have done me was a ſufficient incentive to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all my ſtrength to have made their Villany as notorious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> poſſible; Nevertheleſs they ſee, and the World ſees how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I have been to do it; my Reaſons are ſuch as theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> My Wife was againſt it, two of the Accuſers being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> own Siſters, whom ſhe was loth to expoſe to perpetual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y, or to have them ſtand marked to Poſterity for Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rt, though ſhe knew full well, that they vehemently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed for her Blood, could they have got it in any ſuch way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ld advance the Credit of their Revelations; for all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>diſmal encounters ſhe had with them by word and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> when it was once over, ſhe would often ſay, She could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forgive them, and wiſh their Abuſes might be blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of her Memory, except ſo much as might ſtir her up, thankfulneſs for her deliverance; but I conſidered that this was fulfilled that ſaying of our Lord in <hi>Mat. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.36. I am come to ſet a Man at variance againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Father, and the Daughter againſt her Mother, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and a Man's Foes ſhall be they of his own Houſe</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:48750:3"/>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> I was hindred by Thoughts of my own unworthineſs to be the Subject of ſuch a ſtory. It's true, at firſt I looked on i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as an afflicting Providence, but afterward thought it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity far ſurpaſſing my deſerts, that God ſhould chooſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Inſtrument to fight this Battle, and to bring down th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Pride of the Towring lofty Spirit; and when I conſidere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what Perſons our Saviour choſe for his great Apoſtle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. I ſoon infer'd that Omnipotence could conquer by unlikely Inſtruments.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> I thought that Party ſo under the Power of Prejudice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the cleareſt Convictions offered to them would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> like water ſpilt upon the ground, as yet; ſo I thought, if i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pleaſed God that I ſhould live till that Prejudice wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a litle removed, which I knew could not be without l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Experience, I would then give ſome Relation of the Matter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to manifeſt to the World that what I ſhould do, proceed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from a calmneſs of Mind, not from fury, or deſire of revenge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I had large and ſad Experience how hard it was to diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle, and reclaim thoſe that have entertained any thing under the Notion of a Divine Revelation; one might a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well attempt to remove a Mountain as beat them out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Conceit, though ſo utterly falſe as ever the Father of Lyes can invent. Time I hoped would make them mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> flexible, and then this narration would be a word in d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſeaſon, therefore I now haſten to perform my Promiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To theſe the Publiſher adds:</hi> When I received theſe Papers in <hi>London,</hi> I find the Quakers in open Diſcord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> each Party calling the other <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> but not agree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon a Judge of their Controverſy; Would they both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this Story, it muſt lead them to the right and true end of this Strife. <hi>G. K.</hi> is called Apoſtate, but from what? Not from Scripture-Doctrine to which he now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns; but from Quakers fictions; ſo might a Jewiſh or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Gentile Convert to Chriſtianity be called Apoſtate, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſort of Apoſtaſy is every Mans duty. <hi>2 Cor 6.16.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> recriminates that <hi>W. P. &amp;c.</hi> are Apoſtates, but h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> will he prove it, unleſs Scripture be owned as Judge? H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:48750:3"/>be way ſee the grand deluſion, <hi>their pretended immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Revelation</hi> plainly appearing to be Impoſture; ſo that till we have a certain appeal, it's loſt Labour to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue other Points, and to appeal to <hi>G. F.</hi> or to a yearly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ing, he knows is downright Popery. Finding things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this Poſture, and others at work upon this refractory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ple, I think it a Service ſeaſonable, and due to this Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, to ſend them this co-operating Alarm; and hopeful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe in ſome of them a more docile, flexible temper appears, and <hi>G. K.</hi> is ſo far from their arrogant Conceit of Infallibility, or ſpeaking and writing all by imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Inſpiration, that he promiſes to correct his own Books.</p>
            <p>I well know, this touches their <hi>Diana,</hi> and that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>deſt of this Sect never took kindly the leaſt contradiction <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any hand; for they would not ſuſpect themſelves in the leaſt Error; And why then ſhould they bear Oppoſition, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ear perſecution, who cannot err<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> If they be infallibly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, we are all infallibly wrong: But I value not their Rage. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſince I find their Leaders ſo much delight in Father <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alebranch,</hi> and the Sceptical writings of our day; I will not deſpair but they may queſtion whether they have in all things followed a true Light; Never did People ſo ſoon, and ſo egregiouſly depart from their Primitive Form, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ected Simplicity, which (as I ſee one tells them in Print) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es that they were either much out of the way at firſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are ſo now; They cannot act things ſo contrary upon an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>anged Principle; but if changed, then not infallible; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Holy Spirit changes not one tittle of his Oracles. They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what hindred the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> to reform any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e groſſeſt abuſes, <hi>viz.</hi> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt they ſhould confeſs their Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> erred, or needed Reformation: Either then let the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>kers avow their Reformation, or ſhake hands with their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Mother of <hi>Rome</hi> and Brethren of <hi>Trent,</hi> but reform <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y cannot, muſt not, till beaten out of this curſed pretence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Divine Inſpiration, the ſtrongeſt hold of the Devil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they may be ſo reſcued is my aim and Prayer; to that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I expoſe herein only what ought to be expoſed, a bloody, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Villany, perpetrated in the Name of the Lord,
<pb facs="tcp:48750:4"/>whereby they utterly forfeit their affected Name of <hi>Friends.</hi> Still I find them buſy to draw unwary Souls into their Net; ſuch there is need to confirm by a loud caution, and they'l accept this Service, though it may be the ſinleſs Friends will not yet bluſh, who knew all this Story <hi>23</hi> years ago, and ſhould have diſclaimed the Actors, but did not. Let them hear or forbear, I do hereby acquaint them and others, that when they pleaſe, I am ready to favour them farther, by ſonding abroad, <hi>1.</hi> One of their own very Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Rolls of Teſtimonies againſt a certain City in this Kingdom, wherein they ſeemed to have aped the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>Jeremiah, Ezekiel,</hi> and <hi>Zechariah,</hi> which I lately mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring found to be above <hi>13</hi> Ells long, and all full.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> And with this a farther Eſſay by a Learned, peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, compaſſionate Friend of theirs, wherein he prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> large from their Prints and Practiſes, that they pretend to no leſs than ſuch Inſpiration as the Lord's Prophets and Apoſtles had of old; yet they have no ſuch Inſpiration. This he argues: <hi>1.</hi> From their many Impertinences and No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſence in their Books, which cannot without Blaſphemy be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the holy Spirit. <hi>2.</hi> From the many flat contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of one ſuch inſpired Pretender unto another, eſpecially their Women. <hi>3.</hi> Their ſcurrilous rayling at their beſt oppoſers. <hi>4.</hi> Their apparent contradictions to plain Scripture. <hi>5.</hi> Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perverſions, and groſſeſt Miſinterpretations of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>6.</hi> Their Novel Opinions not heard before in the Church of Chriſt. <hi>7.</hi> The allowed novelty of their Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, having no pretence to Succeſſion. <hi>8.</hi> Their many Doctrine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> calculated to ſerve Popery, Inſtanced in Nine heads of Doctrine, wherein they agree with Papiſts againſt Scripture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>9.</hi> Notorious Poſſeſſions and Witcherafts. <hi>10.</hi> Many groſs Blaſphemies uttered by theſe ſo inſpired. <hi>11.</hi> Wallowing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> groſs unnatural Sins. <hi>12.</hi> Wild attempts of long faſting and miracles. <hi>13.</hi> Contradiction to all other good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, whom they allow to be enlightened by their ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Spirit.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:48750:4"/>
            <p>I chooſe to try their Patience with this, which alone, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt they open their Eyes, might convince them, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Friends</hi> acted from no Divine Inſpiration, but a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>iliſh Tranſport; And can wiſe folks ſtill truſt a notorious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at? Will they ſtill ſcorn the ſure word of Propheſy, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ably fitted to lead them into the way of truth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fe? Are they-all ſo proud and blind? When they mean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ſtly, they will come into clearer light: Mean while, there is one thing that all men muſt think unfair in them, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>as they ſpeak, and act very differently from their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Leaders, they will neither condemn any Actions or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of thoſe Leaders, no, not <hi>James Naylor's,</hi> nor yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or juſtifie them. No ingenuous Man refuſes to confeſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ault when he diſcerns it; would they value Scripture, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rov. 28.13, 14. Jam. 5.16. 1 Joh. 1.9, 10.</hi> there it's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and exemplified often, and appoſitely to this caſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s thoſe Converts, <hi>Act. 19.18, 19, 20. David,</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ter, Kings, Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did often fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Errors, and retract them; Nay, and <hi>G. K. Pag. 31.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Narrative hath theſe Words (well ſuited to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Practiſe) <hi>he that teſtifies not againſt a thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en there is juſt Occaſion for it, juſtifies it.</hi> What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ails our Quakers, that they'l confeſs no Sin to God or Man? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or laſt, they ſhall. But what hinders them now? What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this proud pretence, to act all by Divine Inſpiration? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y are all for bearing their Teſtimonies againſt others, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> why not impartially againſt wickedneſs among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? Diſown it if you think it ſo, and diſown its Principle: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> if n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, the World muſt ſay, and juſtly too, that ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> like ſuch Principles and Practiſes, only you dare not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Such a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> need to be farther acquainted with the very Heart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Quakeriſm, and the deſigns for which it pleaſed wiſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ce, to permit that unchriſtian Spirit to go abroad at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a time, I beg to inform themſelves from two very ſmall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:48750:5"/>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> A Survey of Quakeriſm; by the excellent Author of the Falfilling of the Scriptures, Printed for <hi>T. Park<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurſt. 1677.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2. John Norton's</hi> brief Tract concerning the Quakers Doctrine. Printed <hi>London 1660.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 4. line 25. read <hi>predicted.</hi> p. 7. l. 8. r. <hi>Hudle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſton.</hi> p. 8. l. 19. for <hi>upon</hi> r. <hi>up,</hi> p. 9. l. 11. r. <hi>then ſend.</hi> ib. l. dele <hi>had.</hi> p. 12. l. 16 and 20 and 22. r. <hi>Penrith.</hi> ib. p. 31. for <hi>within</hi> r. <hi>with them.</hi> p. 13. l. 1. r. 200 <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> p. 14. l. 12. for <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>their.</hi> ib. l. 19. r. <hi>County.</hi> ib. l. <hi>penult.</hi> r. <hi>alſo againſt.</hi> p. 15. l. 28. r. <hi>Liberate</hi> without their. p. 16. l. 12 and 17. for <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>their.</hi> ib. p. 15. for <hi>ſued</hi> r. <hi>ſerved.</hi> p. 21. l. 8. for <hi>lift</hi> r. <hi>left.</hi> p. 23. l. 13. r. <hi>Counties.</hi> p. 24. l. 21. r. <hi>Slee.</hi> ib. l. 26 r. <hi>Multitude for.</hi> p. 25. l. 2. d. <hi>your.</hi> ib. l. 3. r. <hi>notoriouſly.</hi> ib. marg. r. 29. p. 26. l. 28. for <hi>where</hi> r. <hi>when.</hi> p, 27. l. 6 for <hi>on</hi> r. <hi>one.</hi> p. 29. l. 17. r. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. ib. l. 20. d., p. 31. l. 7. for <hi>there.</hi> r. <hi>their.</hi> ib. l. 17. for <hi>Scriptures</hi> r. <hi>Scripts.</hi> p. 32. l. <hi>antepe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ult.</hi> r. <hi>Event.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48750:5"/>
            <head>THE NARRATIVE.</head>
            <p>THERE were two Women, the Name of the one was <hi>Margaret Bradley,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Thomas Bradley</hi> of <hi>Knipe</hi> in the Pariſh of <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ton,</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y langhorn,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Thomas Langhorn</hi> of <hi>Helton</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Pariſh of <hi>Askam,</hi> was the other, both in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nty of <hi>Weſtmoreland.</hi> Theſe two turned Quakers moſt with the firſt in the North, and became very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ous among them, having attain'd ſuch boldneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their profeſſion, that they went Preaching and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ting up and down the Country, and became very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>bleſom both to Magiſtrates and Miniſters, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſages they pretended they had from the Lord unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>In the year 1673, in harveſt-time, When I <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ler</hi> was among my Reapers, the ſaid <hi>Margaret Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> came unto me, deſiring me to ſtep aſide that ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t ſpeak with me; I did ſo: Then ſhe told me ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Meſſage from the Lord God unto me; and bid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> obſerve her, for what ſhe had to ſay ſhe had it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt. Well, ſaid I, ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; and thus ſhe proceeded. <hi>I have ſeen by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation of Jeſus Ceriſt that thou art a Murderer;</hi> being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>reat aſtoniſted, I asked, Why? Whom, or What are I Murdered? She anſwered, <hi>The Lord hath Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to me, that thou tookeſt thy own Child by the Neck from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mb of her who is now thy Wife, and Murdered it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bid it.</hi> Then, ſaid I, the Lord rebuke thee, thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>dent Wretch, I am as innocent in this matter
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48750:6"/>as the Child yet unborn. This ſhe regarded not, but went away. Not long after the aforeſaid <hi>Mary Lang, horn</hi> being my Wive's Siſter, came and told my Wife, that the ſelf ſame thing was Reveal'd to her, and <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all which</hi> Margaret <hi>had ſaid was truch, and ſhe would ſenl it with her blood;</hi> This ſhe urged in many Words affirming that they were the <hi>ſaithful and true Witneſſe and Meſſengers of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Therefore ſaid ſhe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, confeſs it, and God will pardon you, for b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> can pardon great ſins, as well as little ones; fear no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> confeſs, and you ſhall Find mercy.</p>
            <p>My Wife took it very ill at firſt, that her near<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Relations ſhould hunt after her Life without any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of cauſe; but being conſcious of our perfect In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, we made our appeal to the Searcher of Hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who in due time hear'd our Prayers, and gave <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtrength ſufficient to go through this bad rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with Courage and Chearfulneſs, ſtill comforting ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> other with this, that God was above the Devil, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in time they would be made manifeſt; which (Ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed be God) accordingly came to paſs; Mean wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with good Confidence we oppoſed them, to convi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them, if poſſible, by all the Arguments we co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> uſe, that their pretended Revelation came from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Devil, that Lyer from the beginning, and the Fat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Lies, who never yet invented a greater Lye th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> this, and that it was Blaſphemy to father it upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God of Truth; Therefore, ſaid we, be perſwaded t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God ſent you not; with much more to this purp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which we might as well have ſpoke to the ſtones, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Wind; for thoſe Women would hear nothing againſt themſelves, and ſo went their way: So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> weeks after this they return'd both together, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaid, <hi>They had now a Meſſage from the Lord, and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eaſy one, which we might eaſily do;</hi> ſaid they, <hi>you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bow to us, and confeſs us to be true Propheteſſes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pray for the dead Child that you have Murder'd, ſo you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48750:6"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall be united in one. This you muſt do, for it is God's Lay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant, between God, and us, and you, and muſt be here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ealed up, and ſhall never be diſcover'd to the World, if you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll ſubmit to theſe eaſy Terms.</hi> We anſwered, Ah poor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aded Creatures! Shall we bow to you, and confeſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t to be true, which we know to be falſe, and pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that which never yet was? Theſe eaſy Terms are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hard for us; we know no Guilt; you are falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>teſſes, the God of truth never ſent you with ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to us, be convinced of your error before you go <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> farther; but I think the Devil has already led <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo far, that he cannot bring you off without ſhame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> confuſion: Thus we parted the ſecond time.</p>
            <p>After a while theſe Women ſent us a Letter begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thus, <hi>The Word of the Lord came unto me ſaying, write <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Henry Winder, <hi>and ſay, the Lord has given thee yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> days to make away thy Goods and La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds to thy Children, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to ſettle thy Concerns, for I have h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar'd, I have hear'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bleating of the Sheep, and the lowing of the Oxen, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſtruction, deſtruction will unavoidably come upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at the end of</hi> 40 <hi>days.</hi> Thus they commonly began <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Letters, which to inſert wou'd be tedious, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the moſt part they were jointly concern'd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> I returned an Anſwer, in order to perſwade them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> quiet at home, and mind their own buſineſs, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> purpoſe; for at the end of 20 days they ſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er Letter, and came alſo to Remember me that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Glaſs was half full, and the other half was f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which will run over and ſpread abroad, and then, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they, 'twill be too late to provide for thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Growing now weary of their repeated fooleries, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was at firſt ſurpriz'd at their brazen-fac'd Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, I only anſwer'd that all their blundring noiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ch was almoſt continual by word, or writing,) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> no terror at all to me; for, ſaid I, I fear ye not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48750:7"/>at all, being ſure you are acted by the Devil, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therefore I will not turn one hoof out of the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for you. Thus the 40 days end came, my Wife wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Letter after Letter to them, hoping at leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> prevail upon her own Siſter, and ſhe had often cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to thank God for unexpected aſſiſtance therein; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtill they made nothing of all ſhe could ſay.</p>
            <p>All this while (which was about a year) the mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> was but little blazed abroad, ſave that the Women <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> communicated it to ſome of their Friends, raiſing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Expectations that it would mightily Conduce to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Honour of their Religion; and by this time anot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Siſter of my Wife, <hi>Margaret Walker,</hi> the Wife of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ward Walker</hi> of <hi>Soulby,</hi> in the pariſh of <hi>Dacre,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> come into them, and full as Zealous in the cauſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> far more fluent and Eloquent. In this Encounter t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> bid us arm our ſelves for the battle; for, ſaid they, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is the battle of the <hi>Dragon;</hi> put on ſtrength ye pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> profeſſors, advance with your Nobleſt Reſolution, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> know, that the <hi>Lamb</hi> ſhall get the Victory. So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deed he did, and ever will; but how much more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Dragons</hi> than <hi>Lambs</hi> they acted in this matter, let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Reader judge.</p>
            <p>Deſtruction came not at the 40 days end, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had prodicted, So up they rouze, and theſe 3 Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> went to <hi>William Layton</hi> of <hi>Daleman,</hi> Eſquire, Juſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> peace for the County of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> and told <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>They were come with a Meſſage from the Lord God unto</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Well, ſaid he, What's the Matter? Said they, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt ſend for <hi>Henry Winder,</hi> and his Wife, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtion them about a Murder which he hath commi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and, <hi>We ſhall direct thee how, as we have received <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Revelation from the Lord.</hi> According to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and humor the Juſtice ſent his man to me, that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> needs go with my Wife to ſpeak with him, which willingly did; and there we found theſe Women, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:48750:7"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> darged us with Murther forthwith; we cried <hi>Not Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> The Juſtice then Queſtioned them what Proof they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d, they anſwered, they had it by <hi>Revelation:</hi> But, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he, you are now entring upon Law, and muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed according to Law, and your Revelation will be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Proof: Will you therefore Depoſe it upon Oath? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaid they, we cannot be free to take an Oath; then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he, can you prove it by any others? No, ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey; then, ſaid he, What Circumſtances can you of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> that may Evidence the truth of your Charge againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man? <hi>Q.</hi> We only had it by Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> How long ſince was this Revealed to you? Q. Nine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uts after it was done, ſaid they. <hi>L.</hi> Was it a Son, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Daughter? ſaid the Juſtice; they anſwered, That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>as not yet Revealed to them; but one of them a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> after told him, it was a Son, and began to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> as murthering the Child, taking it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his left hand, the Knife in his right, and therewith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tting its Throat; but in ſome former Revelations, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey ſaid, they ſaw him ſtopping its Breath with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>apkin. What, ſaid the Juſtice, had you no thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this before? they ſaid, No. When he had their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>arge, and obſerved their inſolent Behavior, he turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to us, ſaying, You hear theſe Women charge you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h Murther, ſure there is ſomething in it, how will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> clear your ſelves? I ſaid, they may charge upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what they pleaſe, we are purely innocent in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tter. The Juſtice obſerving us to be undaunted by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is infamous Charge and Vexation, ſaid then to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>men; according to your deſire, I have Queſtioned <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>vy,</hi> and his Wife, and I find in them nothing but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ocence; What can I do for you in this caſe? No, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o, ſaid they, he is not Innocent. Then ſpeaking to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ny Langhorn,</hi> he enquired how ſhe perceived the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ded Revelation, or how it proceeded, what Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ns attended, and after what manner it had its Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tion? <hi>Mary</hi> anſwered, <hi>She could not well tell, but ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſure it began in her Feet.</hi> Then, ſaid he, What would
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48750:8"/>you have me do? <hi>Anſw.</hi> We deſire thee to get us them to the Aſſize at <hi>Carliſle,</hi> (which was now <hi>Aug.</hi> 1674, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and there will a Spirit riſe at the left hand of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Judge, that will teſtify for us. But, ſaid he, will yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be tied to follow them? <hi>Anſw.</hi> We cannot ſwear, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> we will be there: Well, ſaid he, I'le engage that <hi>Har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and his Wife ſhall be there too: This was about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Week before that Aſſize. And now theſe Women mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> tily beſtir themſelves, and had quickly got a gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> party of <hi>Friends,</hi> inclining to their Opinion ſo far, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to declare them true Propheteſſes; as <hi>John Slee</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a great Speaker in their Meetings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> would ſeal their Teſtimony with their Blood. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> wrote their Accuſation againſt me, and my Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> which they caſt here and there in Towns and Stre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> where they came, and at <hi>Carliſle</hi> gave one of thoſe Pap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to my Lord Judge (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir.... <hi>Wild,</hi> and Baron <hi>Rainsf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> as I remember, were then our Judges.) He only b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them proceed according to Law, and they ſhould h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Juſtice. Mr. <hi>Layton</hi> and Mr. <hi>H</hi> told my Lord wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Quakers appeared, and that they ſaid a Spa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> would ariſe at his left hand, to prove the Murthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then, ſaid my Lord, all the People will ſee and hear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> And now there was great Expectation among them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Spirit, they ſaid, ſhould riſe to teſtify for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and in truth, what they ſpoke, they gave out with ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> aſſurance, as made ſome indifferent perſons either <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lieve them, or at leaſt ſuſpect us. Hence multitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> came into <hi>Carliſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to ſee this Wonder, but all were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ceived, for nothing appeared: Nevertheleſs we ſtay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in Town all the time of the Aſſize, and when eith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of us could meet any of them, we were ready to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> braid them for creating ſuch Tumults and Diſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; (for now it was every Bodies talk) and ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhould we get any other Anſwer, but <hi>Fear God.</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they perſiſted in their Deluſion without the leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> knowledgment of Error, or any ſenſible Diſcourag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48750:8"/>
            <p>Shortly after this, I ſent for a Writ of Defamation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gainſt theſe three Women and their Husbands; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the mean time they ſollicit another Magiſtrate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>he is Lord of the Mannor, under whom I hold my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd, <hi>viz. Andrew Huddleſtone</hi> of <hi>Hutton-John,</hi> Eſquire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtice of Peace for the County of <hi>Cumberland.</hi> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aring this, let the Writs reſt till they had their full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>utſe: Being come to Mr. <hi>Huddlſteon,</hi> they told him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the firſt place, that it was Revealed to them that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhould have my Land: They went alſo to <hi>Bernard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſol-bride,</hi> then Sheriff of the County, and told him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> like Revelation that he muſt have my Goods. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir Spirit moved them to believe theſe Motives <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>old ſtir theſe Gentlemen to do their utmoſt for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. To Mr. <hi>Huddleſton,</hi> they ſaid, God hath decreed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, and we hope thou wilt do us luſtice, in diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ring the Murther which <hi>H. W.</hi> hath committed, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>od will be Gloriſied in his Deſtruction Mr. <hi>Huddleſton</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d, What would you have me do? ſaid they, <hi>Get us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en bither, for we have now revealed Witneſſes, that will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſy the Truth of what we laid to their Charge. We know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> That <hi>Elizabeth Robinſon,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſe of <hi>Thomas Robinſon,</hi> living in the ſame Mannor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Pariſh knows all this, being Bed fellow to <hi>H. W</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſe when the thing was done, and 'tis Revealed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that ſhe hath told it to her Husband Alſo that <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſtopher Wilton</hi> and his Wife, being next Neighbours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll. <hi>W.</hi> know the ſame. Therefore we deſire thee, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed for theſe four to teſtify this Truth. But firſt of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Hudal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſion</hi> ſent for me, while the Women were in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s Houſe, told me their Errand, and that he had no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ind to meddle between us: To whom I ſaid, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ech you Sir, take this trouble upon you, give them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>kir own way in every thing, do as they direct you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſpare not me, try me to the uttermoſt; then, ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, I will, and told the Women, <hi>H. W.</hi> is come, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re will not ſend for the Witneſſes to day, for it is late,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48750:9"/>and we ſhall not have time to examine the Matter. Therefore we'll appoint another day, and I'll ſend f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> all your Witneſſes; which he did. On the Day a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> pointed we all met: Now the Quakers had giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Mr. <hi>Huddleſton</hi> in Writing particular Directions h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to Examine every Witneſs, and the very Queſtions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was to put to each, accordingly he examined the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> one by one, and ſo carefully, that he would not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one hear what another ſaid: I, nor my Wife, nor a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of our Party (as they called them) were permitted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be preſent at the Examination, but only the Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, who threatned the Witneſſes, thatif they wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not ſpeak the Truth they muſt be hanged too. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> being upon Oath, cried out with Amazement, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould we be Queſtioned about a Thing we know no more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> than the Child in the Mother's Womb;</hi> in which mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with like Expreſſions they all agreed, telling the Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers that doubtleſs they were <hi>Bewitched.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being done, Mr. <hi>Huddleſton</hi> called upon me a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> my Wife, with his own Family, and many Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, who were in his Hall come to hear this W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſaid thus to the Quakers, Have you had Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice now? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes. Then, ſaid he, were theſe W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes revealed to you by the ſame Spirit, as the oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Things were? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, by the very ſame. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſaid he, 'tis a falſe lying Spirit, believe it no mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Anſw. <hi>Yes, we will believe it ſtill, for we can go to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place where it was buried.</hi> This word dropt unawa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from them, and they could have been content to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it fall; but when I heard them mention a place, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired Mr. <hi>Huddleſton</hi> to hold them to their Word, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſo they might manifeſt themſelves yet more; whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> upon he Queſtioned them, Where was that place<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. They ſaid, it was revealed to them, That <hi>H. W.</hi> buri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Child on <hi>Sparkhead-Moor,</hi> a place about a Mile <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from Mr. <hi>Huddleſton</hi>'s. That's a vaſt place, ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he, it will be impoſſible to find it, without more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48750:9"/>Directions; go again therefore, and conſult the Spirit; for if there was a Murther, and God intends this way to diſcover it, the Spirit will certainly ſhow you the very place, and by the ſurface of the ground <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> will appear, though many Years ago. Thus they departed, and came again, ſaying, now the very place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s revealed to them; and now there was a deep Snow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd Froſt, ſo that they could not proceed; in which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne they often viſited Mr. <hi>H.</hi> who at length when the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ow was partly off, made them promiſe to be there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a ſet Day, adding, I will ſend my Man to keep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>od Orders, that ye be not diſturbed, (for ſhe ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e was afraid to be troubled in the ſearch by the People) but to me, he ſaid, that I ſhould not go, leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir foolery ſhould provoke me to paſſion. At the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ay appointed they came to the place, with a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ltltude from places adjacent, to hear and ſee what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ould there be done; being met, they were ſlow, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d no great courage to begin the ſearch, but my Wife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>urred them on, and bid 'em chear up, and take cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ge, <hi>for if they had found any Child, ſhe would be content <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſer death for it:</hi> Thus ſhe upbraided their faintneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d folly; but many blamed her, for they who had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aved themſelves ſo deviliſhly all along, who knew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat they might have laid there? To which ſhe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>red, ſhe made no doubt but God was above the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>vil: So they being greedy of her life took courage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> proceed, hoping ſtill to get honour to their Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ns by our death; ſo <hi>Margaret Bradley</hi> drew a Circle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th a ſtaff of about 10 yards circumference, and ſaid <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e had it by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, that the Child <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> within that place;</hi> and ſo got ſome to begin to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ork, but the ground proved ſo hard a Gravel, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e indifferent Obſervers deſired them to ſhift to a ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> place; and they not being able to dig any farther, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>parted with ſhame and confuſion.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:48750:10"/>
            <p>Note here, that <hi>Mary Dawſon</hi> (who was afterwards <hi>Mary Langhorn</hi>) long before this came one morning by break of day to my houſe, my Wife being gone that night to a Neighbour in Travail: ſhe called at the doors and Windows, and told me ſhe would do me no harm, I told her, that was little of my Fear; whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I came to the door ſhe asked me if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> knew any thing of the<note n="*" place="margin">A ſort of fuel digged out of the earth.</note> 
               <hi>Peat-mow</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> What <hi>Peat-mow,</hi> ſaid I, doſt mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I know nothing of it: Yes, but tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doſt, ſays <hi>M. L. For 'twas there th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> didſt</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">i. e. <hi>hide.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>feel the Child, as it is reveale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to me;</hi> yet this very Woman after wards did averr, that the Child was buried as afore ſaid. Being thus miſerably diſappointed. and deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to get my life this way, becauſe none of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Revelations would hold, the aforeſaid <hi>M. L.</hi> my Wife <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> eldeſt Siſter came by night, and calling upon my Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> deſired to ſpeak with her, who ſaid, What art tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not yet weary, what haſt thou yet? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Nothin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but Good for thee, I will aſſure thee, I'le do thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> harm, ſo ſhe went to her; then ſaid M. L. <hi>I have ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> I have ſeen, by the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt that thy H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> band will certainly deſtroy thee, and that he will hang <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Neck for it, and that thy Children ſhall be left deſolate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall be ſcattered and it in other folks</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Chimney corners.</note> 
               <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and none ſhall have compaſſion on the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Go, Go, ſaid my Wife, I have ſo goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> experience of your Revelations, that if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d doubted my Husband's Love, I ſhould now doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it no more: As for my Children, I hope God will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for 'em, and I have better hopes of them, becauſe that Spirit has always been a Lyar; but I ſee it's i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vain to talk; we muſt take another courſe with you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> once more I adviſe thee to go home, and be quiet and abide with thy family, and keep thy Children to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as long as thou canſt; Let the Lord do with me what he will, I am his own, and I fear him n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:48750:10"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all; take thee no care for me, for he will do it; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed as for thy Threats, I fear 'em the leſs becauſe thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eakſt 'em.</p>
            <p>Thus they continued time after time; ſometimes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce, and ſometimes another, and ſometimes 2 or 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gether came to me with their pretended Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s and Meſſages, and telling me they were the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uments that God had Choſen to diſcover all my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cret Villanies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that now when all their old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es failed, they had new Revelations that I was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ilty of the death of ſome perſons nearly related to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em and me: I could not forbear to bewail my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ppineſs, who had already waded through a ſea of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oubles and reproaches, a burden intollerable, had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not been ſupported by a God of truth, and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ear conſcience, that ſtill the Devil ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ffer'd to throw ſo many of his envenom'd darts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> me; nor cou'd I chooſe but be concerned, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oſe perſons for whom I once had ſo great a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, ſhou'd be ſtrayed into ſuch a Wilderneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rror, that I thought it next to impoſſible they ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er find the way out. Reaſon was now ſo taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m them, that the Devil could make them believe any thing: Yet I thought it much more happy to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>us abus'd, than that I ſhould have been an abuſer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>al that this burthen was far eaſier to bear, than a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ilty Conſcience would have been, though no Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the World had known it; I can ſafely call God to Wtneſs, that if ever I knew any in the World, for whom I would have ventur'd my Life to do them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood, it was theſe very perſons the Devil made my Accuſers; ſo ſadly were they bewitched and led cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive by him at his will; and now that no manner of Arguments, nor their own experience of ſo many hameful diſappointments, would move them to any obſervable ſence of their Deluſions, I reſolv'd to jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle no more; but conſidering what loſs I had ſuſtain'd
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48750:11"/>by the aforeſaid Women, and that many other <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> eſpecially their own Husbands were intoxicated by their Diabolical Eloquence, yea, and that they had bred ſome ſuſpicion of me for a while in others of their acquaintance, we thought it reaſonable to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed according to Law againſt them, and both to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover our Dammage, vindicate our Good Name, and publickly to manifeſt the workings of their Fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Spirit; whereupon I brought my Action of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famation againſt the 3 Women and their Husbands <hi>Thomas Langhorn</hi> for default of appearance ſuffer'd a Judgment. <hi>H. W.</hi> having declared againſt him for 300 <hi>l.</hi> Damage. This was obtained 25 and 26 <hi>Carol.</hi> 11. and at the ſame time a <hi>Writ of Enquiry</hi> came down<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whereupon a Jury was impannel'd, which ſat at <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cith</hi> in the County of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> Mr. <hi>William William</hi> of <hi>Johnby-Hall</hi> Gent. being Foreman, Mr. <hi>Robert Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and other principal men of <hi>Pencith</hi> made up moſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Jury, who being met on a day appointed at <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Robiſons</hi> of <hi>Penriſh</hi> to examine the matter, I deſire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the two Juſtices aforementioned to inform the Jury what they knew of the matter; they both came, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> before the Jury gave a full account of the particular<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tranſacted before them, after them <hi>John Noble</hi> (wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was Deacon of that Church I had left, and now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to again; Dr. <hi>Richard Gilpin</hi> now of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> being then our Miniſter in the Pariſh of <hi>Graſtock</hi>) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his Knowledg being as much concerned as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Juſtices; for he was within at all the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations and Aſſizes, and received ſeveral long Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from them, and longer Diſcourſes, from all which he gave a full account of the whole Buſineſs of all their Revelations, Accuſations and miſerable Events; alſo of the Reputation of the party charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he was always accounted a very faithful ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Man, and that he had for a long time experienced him to be ſo;the Gentlemen of the Jury having full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in theſe reports, after a little Deliberation,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48750:11"/>gave a Verdict for me, and 200 Damages. <hi>Eaſter Term.</hi> 26. <hi>Car.</hi> 11. the Writ of <hi>Enquiry</hi> was Executed, and Judgment thereupon, and afterwards Execution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, entered <hi>Rotulo.</hi> 1578. where it may ſtill be ſeen in Mr. <hi>Winford</hi>'s Office in the Common Pleas, as alſo all other Records in this Caſe hereafter mentioned. Now <hi>Thomas Langhorn</hi> and his Wife had before this made ſale of their Goods, and were gone up to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> but imployed <hi>John Mounſey</hi> of <hi>Patterdale</hi> to be their Attorney, and Mr. <hi>James Bird</hi> of <hi>Browham,</hi> now a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of Peace for the County of <hi>Weſtmoreland,</hi> was <hi>B. W</hi>'s. Attorney. At <hi>London</hi> they ſtayed about a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear. When they came home we arreſted them; but they ſtill were very obſtinate and ſcorn'd to pay any thing; to Priſon they would go, poſſeſs'd of their old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oud Error, and ſo to <hi>Carliſle</hi> they went, and remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed Priſoners almoſt Five Years, practiſing their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed Paſſive Obedience and Glorying in it. At length time and experience a little humbled them, ſo that ſame Confeſſions they would make that they had done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s wrong, but none proportionable to the Heinouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Crimes; yet my Wife being moved with natural Affection towards her Siſter, notwithſtanding her former malignity againſt her, did daily ſollicite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to let them come forth, which accordingly I did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a very ſmall part of my Damage, they being a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more humbled at laſt to ask Pardon; for I reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved till they made Submiſſion, or paid the Money, there they ſhould ſtay; 'twas not the Money I deſired, but their Repentance, which in part I have now ſeen; more than once I expected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> That this <hi>Mary Langhorn</hi> was formerly the Wife of <hi>John Dawſon</hi> of <hi>Hutton-John,</hi> after whoſe death ſhe did at divers times expreſs to <hi>H. Winder</hi> (then a Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dower) her great Affection to him, and deſire to have him for her Husband; but his Love was ſet on her young Siſter <hi>Anne,</hi> his preſent Wife, ſo rejected
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48750:12"/>
               <hi>Mary</hi>'s Sollicitations, which enraged her to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that ever after, her anger was implacable. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhe took another Husband, and in Priſon ſhe bar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him Twins, a Son and a Daughter: and to manifeſt her willful impenitence, or immortalize her infamy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhe Named one, <hi>Innocent Priſoner,</hi> and 'tother, <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Sufferer,</hi> ſo firm was her deluſion yet, tho' they could not in all this time chuſe but have many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions, ſeeing there was not from the beginning t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the end any one accident that might cauſe them t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hope for other reward than loſs and ſhame. Every thing contradicted their deſign, had the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been awake, or ſound and clear; but that and their conſcience were perfectly ſtupifyed; but at laſt ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thaw'd a little, for the Friends ſaw it diſhonoure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them all: This <hi>Mary</hi> lives yet in <hi>Helton,</hi> and is quiet.</p>
            <p>During their Impriſonment, I brought my Action 1. Againſt <hi>Tho. Bradley</hi> and <hi>Margaret</hi> his Wife, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lived in another Country, and poor, Skulking i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> holes. <hi>Term. paſchae.</hi> 26. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. I had an exigent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and <hi>Mich.</hi> following actually out-law'd them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Term. paſchae.</hi> 27. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. a Declaration againſt <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Term. Trin.</hi> 27. <hi>Ejuſdem Regis,</hi> I obtain'd Judgment, and a writ of Enquiry.</p>
            <p>At length I had them into <hi>Appleby</hi> Goal, but ſome of their Friends got them out by a Trick, ſo they run away, and as I heard, lived miſerable poor. I knew they were not able to pay, ſo leaſt they ſhould die in Priſon, I took them up no more; this is the Exit of the 2d. couple of my accuſers. 2. I brought my Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt <hi>Edward Walker</hi> and his Wife: he put in his appearance, ſo the Cauſe came to Tryal at common
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48750:12"/>Law at <hi>Carliſle.</hi> When they ſaw I had proof ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to caſt them, they informed their Councel that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 200 <hi>l.</hi> damage granted me before, on the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; and by this the Judge was moved thus to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the Jury. Gentlemen, You ſee the plaintiff has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oved ſufficiently that this Woman hath ſpoken and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſuch things, as if proved, might have taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny his Life, but ſhe makes no proof, ſo that he muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> found damnify'd. Yet becauſe he hath had 200 <hi>l.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ted him before, and becauſe ſhe is a Woman (and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e all have Wives) you muſt be moderate in the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age: Hereupon the Jury brought me in 10 <hi>l.</hi> Damage, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> allowed me coſts of Suit. <hi>Term. Trin.</hi> 26. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. had this Iſſue entred <hi>Rotulo.</hi> 495.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Michaelmas</hi> following I obtain'd Judgment upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dict aforeſaid, and Execution againſt the Body of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er</hi> and his Wife. <hi>Trin.</hi> 28. <hi>Ejuſd. Regis, a Scire Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> againſt <hi>Walker,</hi> and then a Judgment thereupon <hi>Michaelmas</hi> following; all which I again mind the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ious Reader, that he may ſee with all my Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tions againſt them, on Record in Mr. <hi>Windford</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffice.</p>
            <p>Nothing would pleaſe <hi>Walker</hi>'s Zeal, but to be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fering Witneſs too for the ſame glorious Cauſe, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Priſon I ſent Him and his Wife, where they ſtaid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cannot ſay, till they were willing to pay me, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill a good <hi>Samaritan,</hi> as they call'd him, paid the Money, and got them a Liberty without the Licenſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho I think afterwards wiſhed he had not ſo done; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t they were not half Humbled, nor would acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it a Kindneſs, nor repay the Money, leaſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſhould confeſs ſome Fault, though ſo ſmall a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was eaſy for them to pay; however at laſt they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ffer'd him to take it.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:48750:13"/>
            <p>Spiritual pride it ſeems by this was ſtill predom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in them, they would not draw any ſuſpicion u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their infallibility and perfection, and hence not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> jot more of Condeſcenſion could ſo obliging a perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> obtain of theſe ſtomachful Friends; I hope long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Time and Experience (if it has not yet) will ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them wiſer in all things, and ſo bring them and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtians of different perſuaſions into a nearer Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borhood and Union; that as there is but one G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> there may be but one Faith, one way, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God graciouſly diſcover to all my proud Enemy more of the Errors and grievous miſcarriages, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> had need like <hi>Peter</hi> or <hi>David</hi> to Weep bitterly, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> repent in Duſt and Aſhes; and the good Lord pard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them, for they knew not what they did, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they knew not whom: through the Grace of God I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> freely forgive them all. As for the bloody Thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Deſtruction to come upon me and mine from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Lord, I find to my Comfort, that the Curſe cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall not come, as they alſo may obſerve: I know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Bleſſings and Curſes are not theirs to diſpoſe of; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> kept in wiſer hands; hitherto the Lord of his inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> free Mercy prolongs my days with my Dear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Faithful Wife and Children, whom he hath increa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> preſerved and abundantly Bleſſed; my whole Fan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he hath ſpared as a Father ſpares his own Son <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſerves him. And this I declare, as I am bound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the praiſe of his Goodneſs and Truth, and to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> my Seal to his fure Word; <hi>That in the fear of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is strong Confidence, and his Children ſhall have a pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Refuge,</hi> Prov. 14.26.27. Alſo that <hi>in the way of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is life, and in the Path-way thereof is no D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Prov. 12.28. Now that this Story may be a Cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to all that heard or now read it, to walk humbly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, and beware of groundleſs extreams, is the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48750:13"/>of him that's an unfeigned lover of all good Chriſtians.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Houſe in</hi> Hutton-John, <hi>in the Pariſh of</hi> Graiſtock, <hi>and County of</hi> Cumb. <date>
                     <hi>this 9th. of</hi> July, 1696.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Henry Winder.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <p>
               <hi>William Layton</hi> Eſq; dyed ſoon after theſe things were done; others atteſt as follows.</p>
            <p>So much of the Tranſactions herein ſet down as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es to my ſelf, is true,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Witneſs my Hand, <hi>Andrew Hudleſtone.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <p>In Teſtimony of the Truth of all the Material <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſages related in this Narritve of <hi>Henry Winder</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>gle with the Quakers, and particularly of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th on <hi>Sparkhead-moor,</hi> and the Tryal at <hi>Carliſle,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſet our Hands,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Noble</hi> of <hi>Penruddock,</hi> all in <hi>Graiſtock.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Adam Bird</hi> Seni. <hi>of the ſame,</hi> all in <hi>Graiſtock.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Atkinſon</hi> of <hi>Motherby</hi> School-Maſter, all in <hi>Graiſtock.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edward Martin</hi> of <hi>Dacre</hi> Adjacent,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Hedſhon</hi> then of the ſame,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Robinſon</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his Wife of <hi>Todrick,</hi> within named, are alſo yet living there.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48750:14"/>
            <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THE Survivers of my Accuſers remain Quac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers ſtill, but very quiet, ſpeak little of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, deny Perfection in this Life, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> well they may; Pretend a reverend Eſteem of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Scriptures; yet hold many odd Fancies, as, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Heathens who never heard of Chriſt with the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ear, (as they term it) may yet be go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtians, if they obey the Voice of Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but they will not take the Scriptures for the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Rule. What is within ſaid of their many Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> charges, and Revelations, with the Approbation a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Aſſiſtance of many other Quakers, doth ſufficient<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> evince the dangerouſneſs of their Spirit. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> farther Caution, and to ſatisfie ſuch as probab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> will enquire why they chooſe me for their M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to ſhoot at, I think it not impertinent to declare, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> follows.</p>
            <p>I well Remember when that Sect firſt came in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> our Country, ſome of them came into our Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Church, where excellent Mr. <hi>Gilpin</hi> was our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. So bold and reſolute were thoſe Quakers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:48750:14"/>Behaviour, and many of them ſo furniſhed with thwarting Arguments, and croſs Anſwers, that our Learned Miniſter being not yet acquainted with their new Cant, ſeemed to me ſometimes allmoſt at a loſs for Replies; whereupon I, and others of the Church, were ſadly ſhaken, and ſome of us ſo tick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with this new Doctrine, that we withdrew from our former Communion, and appeared to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the Quakers, and herein my Wife was entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and ſeduced with me; this was ſadly reſented <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y our pious Miniſter and People; and on this very Account the Church appointed a Day of Humiliation, the Miniſters and others came to me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d to ſeveral that were now grown disaffected, to deſire us to be there on that day: I think we were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> prevailed with to go; and indeed a day of very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Humiliation, and tenderneſs of heart it proved: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>any that were ſhaken, or ſtood Tottering were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uced, well ſatisfied, and confirmed for the rent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d like to have been very great: I Remember at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> time I was ſo ſatisfied, that I had ſecret reſolves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> comply with the Church, and made ſome open <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecantation, but theſe Convictions ſtay'd not long; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Arguments of the Quakers were continually <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing about me, and ſcarce any thing elſe could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my Audience, ſo that I was quickly again where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as before; upon which ſeveral Meetings were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ointed by the Miniſter, and chief of the Society to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>courſe theſe Matters. I being now much in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y with the Quakers, was grown too hard for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>guments; To them I would go, as <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.24.25. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d to them I did return, and was very conſtant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ith them, I think alſo indifferently well beloved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them. For ſoon after my Entrance among them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y repoſed a great truſt in me, <hi>viz.</hi> to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>et of all their Collections in the County; which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iged me to go frequently to their Monthly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48750:15"/>Meetings for ſeveral Years. By being thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned I had opportunity to diſcourſe with many o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them from every Quarter, whereby I found a very great change from what was at the beginning<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much Jarring, and Diſcord, ſecret envyings, and different Opinions; This cauſed much diſquiet an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> anguiſh in my Mind, and put me upon a ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Examination of the Grounds of Religion: There<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> I conſidered both what I had renounced, and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it was I now entertained in the room thereof. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> remember that the firſt thing that induced me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> leave Communion with the Church, was a Conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>That the Scripture was not the word of God,</hi> for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Word was God himſelf; and the Scripture a de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Letter, and the Letter kills; therefore I thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Scripture could not be the Rule of Faith a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Worſhip; and that ſuch as teach by it, muſt be bli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Guides, and if the blind lead the blind both muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> together. The Rule to which I thought I was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> take heed was a light within; there was the word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God directing me what I muſt do to be ſaved; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I judged it needleſs to do, or know any this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which that Light ſhewed not to be neceſſary, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> by that Light I ſaw no Neceſſity of outward Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; ſo concluded they were but Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Men, and not to be regarded, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> being the Foundation of my Relapſe to Quakeri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> I next conſidered why others oppoſed this my N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> on, as my ſelf had once done; And I found t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> oppoſed the ſufficiency of this Light within from Belief that God had given the Scriptures for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſufficient Rule, and that the Scriptures contai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> all things neceſſary to be believed and practiſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had no way to prove the ſufficiency of my Lig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> but by the Scripture, which I fancied referred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to it; ſo this revived my Suſpicion of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, eſpecially conſidering it was to no purp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48750:15"/>Men to teach any Doctrine which they could pretend no Scripture for, this forced this Inference upon me, <hi>If all Doctrines muſt be proved from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, then doubtleſs Scripture is the Rule,</hi> but I ſee 'tis, and it muſt be ſo; Therefore I cannot avoid this concluſion, <hi>That the Scripture is the Rule,</hi> and if it be, then <hi>here</hi> was my firſt Miſtake: This made me Remember who they were I had lift, even <hi>Thoſe that taught this very Doctrine;</hi> And then may I left them, and that was at Firſt, <hi>becauſe they taught this Doctrine;</hi> Thus I proceeded from one conſideration to another, to a freſh view of the Sacraments; for when I could not eſcape the foreſaid concluſion (though it went much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my Mind) that the Scripture was the moſt ſure and perfect Rule, it brought me thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reaſon the Caſe. <hi>If the Scripture be the Rule, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rament of the Lords Supper is ſurely a Duty,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein ſo expreſly required; If a duty, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e I cannot without Sin live in the Neglect of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or condemn others uſe of it; But of all this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I convinced; therefore among the Quakers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> can not ſtay with a clear Conſcience, <hi>&amp;c. I ſhall ariſe and go to my Fathers houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all theſe convictions, I continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to frequent their Meetings, untill I thought <hi>the Lord left me,</hi> or ceaſed to ſhow me my way, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to ſtrive with me to return. Then I fell into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Temptation wherein I was ſo caſt down, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deſpaired to receive Comfort any way, but vnder the ordinances appointed in the Scripture; and now through infinite grace to a great Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlider, I returned to that Church from whence I cameere out, and therein I abide, and ſtand to this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y. This did very much diſpleaſe the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers; for many a call and invitation I had from
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48750:16"/>them to return. When they ſaw nothing would prevail, they began to envy me, and their Love was turned into Malice, which eats like a Canker; from which at laſt broke out the aforeſaid Tragedie. If this was not the thing that ſo incenſed them againſt me, I know not what was, except what I ſaid before of <hi>Mary Dawſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Witneſs my Hand Henry Winder.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:48750:16"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS On the preceeding NARRATIVE: WITH Several other Inſtances of the Quaker's pretended <hi>Divine Revelations,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>A Strange ſtory this is (Reader) indeed, and beyond the power even of Quakers impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to deny, ſince 'twas ſo long tranſact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo many <hi>friends</hi> concerned in it, and not in a corner, but in the open face of two Countrie's; teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd and vindicated at a publick Aſſize. Certainly the Righteous God by permitting ſo ſtrong delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as theſe, deſigned to expoſe to common view the temper and tendency of the Spirit of Quakeriſm; nay, the Devil himſelf (who one would think is ordinarily one of their <hi>Friends.</hi>) ſvern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> here to have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48750:17"/>ow'd them a ſpite, who ſo long by ſo enchanting ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions, mannag'd theſe Perſons to the ſhame of the whole Sect.</p>
            <p>That none may read ſo memorable a thing as common News; nor miſs of ſome good fruit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, I annex ſome Remarks upon it, which ſhall be directed.</p>
            <p>Firſt to the Quakers, or ſuch of them as are moſt concern'd.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe your good is in ſpecial manner here by deſign'd, and to expoſe nothing among you b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> what is perniciouſly evil, I freely declare, If any o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you ſincerely value Scripture-light and Rule, and do not adhere to the guidance of this mad Spirit this ſtory intends not to accuſe you. <hi>H. W.</hi> (as you read above) is ſo juſt and fair to own all that little hopeful amendment he ſaw in his envious perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and the ſounder mind of ſome <hi>Friends</hi> who a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the firſt Aſſize perſuaded the Women to do him right, by confeſſing their Error. One of thoſe ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>John Flee</hi> aforeſaid, he fear'd the matter would iſſue in ſhame to their party; but that great Speaker reprov'd him in theſe words, <hi>doſt thou not hear that they ſay it will bring honour to the truth.</hi> He then believed their prophetical Spirit. But I will nor be ſo Quaker-like as to cenſure a multitude. For ought whereof I can find tollerable proof that moſt are innocent. Show the world your diſlike of this Spirit and Principle, by diſclaiming ſuch who are acted by it, as of late you reject <hi>G. K.</hi> from your Community, and I ſhall charge none ſuch, but (my <hi>Friends,</hi> for why ſhould you not be mine too,) are not you obliged like other men, to ſatisfy the Church of God what rule you walk by? 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15.16.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48750:17"/>and that you entertain no ſuch wild, wicked doctrines? it is your poſitive Duty that you renounce, and bear Teſtimony againſt what is notorious falſe and evil; and every honeſt man readily <hi>comes to the light that it may be manifeſt his deeds are wrought i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God.</hi> Joh. 3.21. So would we all rejoice, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> did over his Children, to ſee you <hi>walking in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aiſtian truth.</hi> 2 <hi>Ep. Joh.</hi> 1.2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Say in earneſt, What think ye of theſe three dear Siſters? True Quakers they were, and owned as ſuch to the laſt: But what Spirit, what Wild-fire is this that they and you have choſe for your Guide? Had not they the ſame aſſurance of being divinely reſpired, as others of you, <hi>i. e.</hi> their own ſtrong Imagination? Now, if hereby ſome were deceived, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay not other Quakers alſo? And will you ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Spirits untried? You expect that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve your Teſtimony; we demand proof by ſound Reaſon, Scripture, or Miracles, that its God's Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nony; and ſuch the Son of God, and his Apoſtles, did not diſdain to give unto <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, our three Women it ſeems were convinced how juſt this is, when they told of a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits appearing for them in open Court,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.24.</note>
               <hi>Wram the Father ſends, he leaves not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> as theſe were left. Your Spirit in this very ſtory <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ers Contradictions, bloody Revenges, and ſneaking carnal Policies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſuch God's Eternal Holy Spirit never did. See then what Spirit ye are of, and be inſtructed by that Man after God's own heart, what to do <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.59.60.176. Leaſt (to evade the Conviction here offered) you alledge, <hi>That this is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gular Inſtance,</hi> and ſo affects not a party, I referr you to an old Book, <hi>The Quaker ſhaken,</hi> and to a late one, <hi>The Snake in the Graſs,</hi> for many more like In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, to which in ſo great plenty, I add a few.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:48750:18"/>
            <p>About the date of this Story, <hi>Peregrine Dalston</hi> of <hi>Ouſton</hi> in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> fell deep in love with a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor Female-friend, and confidently aſſerted <hi>It was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to him, that if he could ſwallow his Bed-ſheet, it ſhould be a Teſtimony to him that he ſhould obtain his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Lamkin:</hi> Well, the poor Wretch obediently at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts it, and (what would the Devil have more) was juſtly choak'd in the tryal. An older, and more crafty Friend was he, that came by like Revelation to <hi>Paul Hobſon</hi>'s Houſe, near <hi>Durham,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The Lord ſent him to Sojourn there, till the Spirit call him elſewhere. Paul Hobſen</hi> was then a Man of figure, and his humor was to entertain any fanciful People a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> few days, ſo bid him Welcome: This Spark it ſeem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo long liked his Quarters, that a Spirit came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Landlord to deviſe how to get rid of his Burt, and this was his Expedient; he ſpake through a Reed into the Enthuſiaſts chamber, ſaying, <hi>Ariſe, and go immediately into</hi> Wales, <hi>where it ſhall be told th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> what thou ſhalt do.</hi> This Friend was ſo loving, that he lay ſtill all night, nor offered next day to depart, till Mr. <hi>Hobſon</hi> ſaid to him, Friend, What ſort of a Voice was that I heard from thy Chamber laſt night<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Anſw. Ah, 'twas a Call of the Spirit to me, &amp;c.</hi> and now I muſt obey it: Which he did. Well-fare <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite Faith.</hi> The Story is not yet beyond the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of Man.</p>
            <p>Nor that doughty Oracle of a <hi>Briſtol-Prophet,</hi> where the late Reverend Mr. <hi>John Paul</hi> was Miniſter of St. <hi>James</hi>'s: That modeſt Friend came naked into the Congregation, with only a Rope about him, and bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing as their manner was: He dropt his Rope, while ſome Sinners that better underſtood the 7th Commandment, caſt a Covering over his ſhame, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him out: By and by comes another inſpired Friend into the Church, crying, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, Give the Mr.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48750:18"/>as Ro-o-pe again. Thus ſaith the Lord, Give the Man his Rope.</hi> A heavenly Propheſy ſure; Ay, indeed, of all things 'twere pitty to rob him of what he beſt deſerved, or moſt needed, to bind him to better <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aviour: Give him his own, and give him his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>William Simpſon,</hi> one of their greateſt Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, walked naked in <hi>Penrith,</hi> with his head ſhaven, and aſhes on it, crying, <hi>Repent, Repent, Deſtruction is as hand.</hi> Likewiſe he went thus through many Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-Towns, and in, or near <hi>Carliſte,</hi> for diſturbing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e quiet People, was taken to priſon; and there he thought he had a Revelation, <hi>That that City ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and be deſtroyed within Ten days.</hi> This he ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, that thereby he affrighted ſome ſo far as to remove their Goods; but a little time diſcovered the Man to be miſerably deluded, and for a publick Offence, he was publickly whipt out of Town. See <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 66.4. They like not this ſport now.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time <hi>Margaret Mark,</hi> Wiſe of <hi>Thomas Mark</hi> of <hi>Soulby,</hi> in the foreſaid Pariſh of <hi>Dacrr,</hi> turning Quaker, renounced her Husband, would not own him, called him <hi>Dog, Devil,</hi> &amp;c. very zealous he was for their way, and conſtant at their Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; but having diſowned her Husband, lived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part with only on Servant, and ſpent her time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly in ſpinning. To this Servant ſhe ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome very fine Linen, telling what ſhe intended it for. <hi>Its written,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>that a Woman ſhall compaſs a Man, and I am the Woman that muſt be Mother to a ſecond Savlour; and this Cloath I have prepared againſt that time to wrap him in.</hi> Believe me, if the Son of God would be born again, and did not like his old Hanger, I would commend him to a Quaker for ſoft and warm Lodging, provided he be but a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48750:19"/>to their tooth. See here how the Devil is ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bleſſed God, but like a bungler, for honeſt, pious <hi>Mary</hi> did cleave to her betrothed Husband. <hi>Matth.</hi> 1. Stay Reader, and ask, How many Chriſts and Saviours will this People at length produce? There was but one to come, and he the Son of God, and born of a Virgin: Now he came long ago, and we look not for another, nor is there is Heaven or Earth ſuch another Son of God, nor can be. I know no need of a Second, nor Fault in the firſt, unleſs this be one, <hi>That he was not born of a Quaker,</hi> nor will be confined to ſave only Quakers, nor will he ſave any (no not Quakers) but in his own way; they muſt value his Blood, and ſubmit to the Rule of his Word; but Quakers like not ſuch Terms, therefore will have a ſecond. I admit that this Woman after ſhe was perverted fell melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a while, but recovered ſoon to act rationally in all matters as ever ſhe had done; after which ſhe lived eight or ten Years, and all the while a Quaker, continuing to abhor her Husband as a Serpent, if at any time ſhe met him: No wonder, for you ſee ſhe expected other Fruit of her Womb, but wofully deceived in the event. Now, ſhall we marvel that Quakers offer us a new Creed, or Chriſtianity, and ſcorn our old Bible, when their Spirit ſays, we muſt have a ſecond Saviour? A <hi>Carnal</hi> one too, and who is <hi>within</hi> none but a ſingle Woman: But he was only in her Imagination, ſo was a <hi>fit Brother to their other Chriſt within:</hi> Well, Is this all? No, we have more Chriſts among them, for <hi>Nailor</hi> owned himſelf to be jeſus the Son of God.</p>
            <p>If they alledge that ſhe, or <hi>M. M.</hi> were melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that ſuch a mind or fancy is a <hi>Balueum Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boli,</hi> I grant the whole, both of theſe and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diviners: But will the Quakers own this Plea?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48750:19"/>Did they ever reject any of their Dreamers or Prophets as ſuch? Did they deal ſo by this Conceiver, or our 3 Propheteſſes or their great Propheteſs in <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> who when one told her the late Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> was dead, ſaid theſe very Words, <hi>Believe it not, I'le tell thee what I have from the Lord, he is as ſurely alive ſtill as any of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> No, no, they reject them not, for theſe are the Tools to amuſe the ſimple: Now, ſay I, what a caſe is theſe people in, without a rule to try the Spirits? Every Jugler, every brain-ſick Demoniack may be their Prophet: Thus you lie at the Devil's mercy, who is not unwatchful to ſcratch where it itches, and improve his advantages. Verily one would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſuſpect that Father of Lies in Torment, did even recreate himſelf by playing upon the creduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch, who are ſaid <hi>to ſport themſelves with their ten deceivings.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 13.17.19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how nearly the Text concerns this People they would do well to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, by comparing, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2.</p>
            <p>But Friends, Memories are not always perfect; therefore wee'l come nearer to the Year, 1686. when another (full of Spirit, no doubt) and upon a large Carnal Pulpit too, or a High-place in that City, uttered this Angelical Preachment. <hi>The Light is broke out in the Minds of Men, and Lo, this is our meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Place;</hi> had he not better have ſaid as another ſince that time, who having deſigned to Speak, the Spirit unluckily forgot to tell him what. <hi>Friends, I have a good Conception, but a very bad Utterance.</hi> Juſt ſo inſpired was that Prophet of yours, who in the Year, 1694. walkt through many Towns and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in this Kingdom, pronouncing Judgments here and there; as particularly at <hi>Briſtol, That in few Months that City ſhould become a Pool of Water, except it did repent;</hi> this was declared amongſt a croud of you; publiſht in the Streets, owned before the May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48750:20"/>whoſe courteſie to the ſilly Wretch others o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you Congratulated, Careſs'd the Man, Honour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Prophecy above the Bible; coppied and hung <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> up in your Houſes; yet I dare Challenge you which of you believed him, or fled out of <hi>Sodom.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> But why did ye not, if he was inſpired and ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from God? And if he was not, then what was h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and you that approved him? and encouraged him o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his way; See 2 <hi>Ep. John.</hi> v. 10.11.</p>
            <p>Now leaſt all or ſome of theſe be ſaid to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure Perſons, and that their perſonal Freaks do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> affect their Party, I deſire it may be remembred from publick undeniable Prints this preſent Year that a very publick Perſon, a great Leader and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite of this People, did openly own this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to immediate Divine inſpiration, as a rule o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Practice; I mean, <hi>William Pen,</hi> in his Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating <hi>G. K.</hi> for he acted by no Written Rule, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pretended ſo, but that a Divine Power came upon him ſo forcible, that he knew not whether he we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Sitting, Standing or Kneeling; and that under th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> power he utter'd that Sentence. How to diſtingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh that Frenzy from this of our Women, I know not: 'Twas all the warrant he had to pronounce <hi>G. K.</hi> a <hi>Heretick</hi> or <hi>Apostate:</hi> How like this Roari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is to that of a Popiſh Bull, let others judge, and what further proceedings againſt <hi>G. K.</hi> a <hi>Penſilvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Magiſtrate might think to juſtifie by a like im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe, I cannot tell; but would not much truſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> good Nature of a provoked <hi>Quaker;</hi> was it not will for <hi>Henry Winder</hi> that his Cauſe depended in an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Court of Juſtice; elſe the Teſtimony of theſe Propheteſſes might have touched his Life, namely before a Magiſtrate diſpoſed to believe ſuch Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: Suppoſe but that his Accuſers or their Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters had been upon the Bench, I demand what ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48750:20"/>he had to eſcape? and the like I ſay of <hi>G. K.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow let them tell us, if they can, what cenſure of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Friends</hi> W. P. has incur'd for his ſo daring Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault of this Man; or wherein this differs from the and Pranks of Old <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> 3 <hi>Ep. John</hi> v. 9.10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what we may judge to be an avowed Act of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> party, if this was not. I know there little Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticies in their methods of acting moſt part, ſo as nothing may be imputable to the party, but lie at be door of this or that ſingle Man, when conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to be diſclaimed; and thus it comes to paſs that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> never know, or ſhall know, what is the Doctrin of <hi>Quakeriſm,</hi> they reſerving a liberty (like the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Lies who is a very changling) to ſhrink from whatever they find unſeaſonable to own: Thus <hi>W. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> is taught by his Spirit, in the Years, 1693. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to divulge ſeveral Scriptures that carry a face <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſubmitting his Doctrines to Scripture Teſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>uting them thence, yea, wherein he would ſeem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay the very ſame concerning the Perſon of Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Reſurrection, for which he pronounces <hi>G. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> an Apoſtate; hoping perhaps that the world had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>got how flatly his <hi>Sandy Foundation ſhaken</hi> oppoſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Doctrines, or that no body would remember <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he ſo lately ſaid in a publick Meeting, <hi>That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſee no need of Preaching the Faith of Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which ſo many Nations receive, and it profits them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but the Faith of Chriſt within.</hi> Whether this be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>able to his novel pretence of valuing and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Scripture, let honeſt <hi>Quakers</hi> judge, by comparing 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17, 18, 23, 24, 30.—<hi>Cap.</hi> 2.2.—<hi>Cap.</hi> 15.2, 3, 4, 11, 12. And what inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration taught <hi>W. P.</hi> this guileful doubling, I wiſh himſelf to conſider; for God is jealous, and the judge is at the Door.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:48750:21"/>
            <p n="3">3. Where will this Spirit lead you? Never to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake this World for Chriſt, whatever <hi>W. P.</hi> tall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>No Croſs, No Grown.</hi> He means no outward Croſſ for that too is to be born within. Never were <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> more buſie and witty to grow carnally Rich; inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> much that I have heard you glory of that ſucceſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a ſure Argument of God's Favour; much like ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Popiſh Marks that their Church is true; God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Spirit leads to God, and to mind Heavenly future things; to follow Chriſt and crucifie the Fleſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which how you do at this Day, they that look with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Families, Kitchins and <hi>Wine-Cellars,</hi> or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſumptuous Houſes, curious Habits, and leathern Conveniencies, do plainly ſee. Now ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> your Spirit aims to get and enjoy theſe pleaſures o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sin and Fleſh, I ask, Where will it lead you for that? Archbiſhop <hi>Whitebread,</hi> and ſuch others, did ſurely mean to return from whence they came ſince then your Spirit, Fancy or Flatus is your ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Rule, its but ſending among you ſome well skill'd in their <hi>Hocus Pocuſſes</hi> (and ſuch you may read in the Hiſtory of <hi>Jetzer</hi>) and then you by war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of your ſort of Revelation, may as well Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> as your own St. <hi>George.</hi> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture its true forbids both; but that's a <hi>Carnal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> made of Paper and Ink,</hi> and the Spirit ſearcheth deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er things: Since Friends of Old and of Late come with pretended Impirations, (and <hi>Rome</hi> too hath her Father's Miſſionary) what have you to try their Spirits? Can none come and ſay, <hi>The Lord ſent them, whom he ſent not?</hi> If ſome may, How ſhall we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern who are ſent? To judge by Scripture is to ſet up a Rule you have been long throwing down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Shall we then judge by the Events, the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or not, of their Predictions? As we are taught <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.22. By this, many more <hi>Quakers</hi> beſides
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:48750:21"/>our three Women, are Notorious, Preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Impoſtors; yet if at ſome time a predict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Event ſhould follow, that's no ſure Rule, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 13.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Namely, <hi>If that Prophet calls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> People from the Law of Moſes,</hi> as you do: I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ſeſs till you return to the Law and the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, I ſee not what ſecurity you have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ſt the moſt Helliſh Illuſions, and Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Suggeſtions. That there is a Devil (<hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit,</hi> in your Cant) your ſelves oft ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs; and Scripture tells you, he's a buſie receiver, a falſe Prophet; that his <hi>Deluſions are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Depths of Satan, Rev.</hi> 2.24. He <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Simon Magus,</hi> and the People too, think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a great man, yea, <hi>the great Power of God,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 8.9, 10. and you cannot forget <hi>Mahomet's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſo long as you ſee ſo many vaſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s believe his Grand Lie. Now, why ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not, as ſoon as a Miſſionary <hi>Quaker?</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your principle I cannot imagine how to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tinguiſh a New from an Old <hi>Alcoran.</hi> In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Aſſemblies you have, and ſtill read Friends <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> therein, but not Scripture; and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> in your Writers hath often charged you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> do ſo, witneſs ſome of their Title Pages: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> then ſpeak out, whether you be not in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Peril as they in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>Giving heed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeducing Spirits and Doctrines of</hi> Daemons, <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> through the Hypocriſy of Lyars,</hi> — as I think, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> text is better tranſlated by ſome.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Does not this Story wonderfully confirm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Doctrine of ſinleſs Perfection? The Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n enjoin their accuſed Brother to bow to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and Confeſs. Ah! the pride of this <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Spirit!</hi> it tells them they muſt Bow to no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but withall it tells them that others muſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48750:22"/>Bow to them; ſo <hi>G. F.</hi> had the Humility to receive Adoration and Worſhip, and <hi>Nailon</hi> too, and juſtify'd it by a pretence that Chriſt was in him: So ſays the Papiſt, he is in a Cruciſix. <hi>Further they muſt be acknowledg'd Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheteſſes too;</hi> Propheteſſes no doubt, for foretelling a Fact 9 Years after 'twas done; nay, in the Authority of their Spirit, they have Popiſhly enjoyn'd the accuſed to <hi>pray for the dead Child</hi> Moreover Self-contradictions and Inconſiſtencie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> confirm their Infallibility; as well as the Pope's One ſays, the <hi>Childs Throat was cut,</hi> another <hi>'twas ſtrangled;</hi> once 'twas <hi>hid in the Peat-mow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and then 'twas <hi>Buried on</hi> Sparkhead-moor, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ſurely no ſearch would be made there Dreadfully they uſurp the Name of God and Jeſus Chriſt in vain; yea more, to vouch their Helliſh Lies and Impoſtures, how audaciouſly and profanely do their Letters imitate the phra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of Scripture? How prodigiouſly is the Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Commandment violated here! It preſcribes Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in all Relations, but here's unnatural contempt and dreadfulleſt breach of Duty to neareſt Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: And what horrid violation of the 6th. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> barbarous thirſting for their Brother and Siſter life! Of the 8th too and 9th, in ſeeking to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them of their Reputation and Eſtate, and to draw them to accuſe themſelves, under colour of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for their Children: Beſides that they ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unweariedly, impudently, bore falſe, deviliſhly falſe Teſtimony before God, Angels and Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> And is this the Perfection of Quakers? Yes, this is it indeed, juſt like that of the bloody ſelf-righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Phariſees, or that in <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.23. to 27 an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 35. Sure they would not have us think the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> void of ſin, if they allow that either they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we know what Sin is. But, mark Reader, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:48750:22"/>hard to know, ſince we muſt have <hi>no Goſpel, no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, no Rule, but within our Selves;</hi> for a wiſer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>an tells us what we all may feel and witneſs in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelves, <hi>That every Man's way is right in his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Prov. 21.2. —<hi>Cap.</hi> 12.15. Even the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ool is wiſe in his own Conceit, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.12, 16. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 28.25, 26. And ſo were theſe great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectioniſts too! <hi>John</hi> 7.48, 49. <hi>John</hi> 9. v. 22. — 34. Theſe indeed in our Story, ſince their Impoſtures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> opened, ſeem to deny perfection in this life, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> will <hi>W. P.</hi> deny it without ſhuffling? Or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>till <hi>G. F.</hi> deny it, who declared himſelf equal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, and receiv'd Worſhip? Remember <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, Reader, as their Infallibility conſiſts with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and Self-contradiction; ſo can their perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſtand with moſt Abominable Wickedneſs. Theſe are the People that confeſs no ſins, nor will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a part in the juſteſt national Humiliations; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, they are devoutly keeping their perpetual <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bath the while in their open ſhops, that no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtomer be loſt. No wonder they ſo perverſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refus'd to join, both in the Year 1689. and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 1696, in giving God thanks for delivering us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our Religion from <hi>French</hi> Tyranny: Againſt <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I and Chriſt without,</hi> they'l bear a Teſtimony, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> none againſt the late King <hi>James</hi> and Popery; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ean, not they of <hi>Pen</hi>'s Faction; for I ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> own that diſtinction, leſt I wrong the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Do we not reaſonably demand an account of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Doctrine concerning Jeſus Chriſt, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oly Spirit, on whom all this ſtuff is fathered, as ſaid by his Inſpiration, or that he had diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> all this to you? If there is no Chriſt but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> you, and that's it you mean, all this may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; for all this lewd ſtuff certainly <hi>came from
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48750:23"/>within,</hi> as <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.18, 19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4.18. If Friends will be ſo pleas'd, I can tell them of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Stanch Quaker at this day ſo juſt and true, that being taken in the fact of Curſing and Swearing freely owned, <hi>'tis not I, but the Devil in me:</hi> So may the Devil dwell and be Friends with the Quakers Chriſt within. But if that <hi>Darkneſs a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Corruption within</hi> (whatever you call it) is your Chriſt, it's the Devil's Chriſt, and God's Chriſt warns you againſt it, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.23. And wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he ſpeaks, the Spirit ſpeaks unto the Churches <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. But who or what is your Spirit? It not ſeems to confeſs Chriſt, and you read that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionally the Devil would do ſo, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.29. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 4.34. If by the Spirit you mean that Divine Eternal Perſon, who ſpake in and by the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Apoſtles, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19, 20. and ſpeaks ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the written Word, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. we know, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is not of him: But if your Spirit is your <hi>preg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> imagination, or a wild Paſſion,</hi> then it's granted th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> were acted by it. But then we that complain of <hi>Socinians</hi> and others, who make the Holy Gh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a Divine Power, Quality or Creature,</hi> muſt mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> more complain of you. Tell us therefore plain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what <hi>ye mean by Jeſus Christ, what ye think of his.</hi> For ye have not told Dr. <hi>Lancaſter</hi> to ſatisfaction. Do you mean the <hi>Light or any thing within you?</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ye are wont when ye tell us, <hi>Chriſt is crucify'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in, riſen and exalted within;</hi> yes, rather crucif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> than exalted, but how <hi>both</hi> I cannot deviſe. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever take that notion with all its Non-ſence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> can this Light, or whatever elſe in you, <hi>be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Christ,</hi> i.e. be a <hi>Saviour, and be Anointed?</hi> for ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of you know that ſo theſe names mean? How <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that Light in you reveal Secrets, ſend Meſſenger (as you call your ſelves, <hi>Witneſſes and Embaſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt?</hi>) Why have not all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:48750:23"/>Quakers ſuch Revelations, or Diſcoveries, ſince they are all furniſht (and we too) with the light within? Is this Chriſt of yours a Perſon, a glorious Lord, exalted at the right hand of God the Father, and ſuch as the Scriptures re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent true Chriſt to be? Then down go the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents moſt of you have ſo long eſpouſed about Chriſt: Yea are Apoſtates from Primitive Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keriſm, and from Father <hi>Fox.</hi> That Jeſus deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed in Scripture was to ſeal up Viſion and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. or to give ſuch perfect diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of God's Counſel and Will to the World, that the Spirit's extraordinary Gifts of Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be no more neceſſary, nor continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. But the Quakers by pretending to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant prophetical Revelation from him, deny his Work aforeſaid; and denying that he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>one his Work, deny <hi>that He is come,</hi> or worſe; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, that <hi>He ever was to come,</hi> or <hi>needs to come.</hi> A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gular Priviledge they have in having their Chriſt <hi>within,</hi> whom there's no danger of forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing in any caſe; 'tis but to conſult their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight, 'twill give a Reſponſe like that, <hi>Cum fueris <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Romano vivito more.</hi> Then enter Father <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and all is done: They may in a new ſenſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as their inward Chriſt will not fail to tell them) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all things to all men,</hi> as already in habits and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tures; ſo may be Papiſts or Turks upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p n="6">6. If you'll grant theſe Women were deceived, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en who deceiv'd them? Was it not that old Maſter of Art, ſo Officious among the Sons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God, <hi>Job</hi> 1. The ſame that beguiled the Corinthians from pure Chriſtian Simplicity, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inth.</hi> 11. If they did err, God and his Spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Truth ſo far left them. And then I think
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48750:24"/>it worth your inquiry, what might be the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions or cauſes of that penal permiſſion, this no more of you be ſo enchanted. One moſt fatally intoxicating notion I take to be, that of the <hi>ſaving Grace of God in all men;</hi> what could men deviſe more proud and provoking, to bring all God's remedial proviſions into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt? I can ſee nothing it ſaves, unleſs they mean that it ſaves them all care and pains i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> working out their Salvation. For no people ſleep ſo ſecure as they, without all fear or Spiritual conflict.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Is it not time to review all the Doctrine and Practices which upon this one Antiſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural conceit you entertain? If you are o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the way, never were men ſo fearfully out no guide ſo ſlippery as that ye have choſen; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> very <hi>Proteus,</hi> as all men ſee, only will not change white. Ye can confeſs or deny Chriſt come in the Fleſh, ye can own or diſown his ſatisfaction and righteouſneſs; value or deride and decry his benefits, Grace and Word <hi>pro re nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> The Antichriſts in St. <hi>John</hi> were honeſt men to you, and yet of them he ſaid, <hi>they had not G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> becauſe they did not <hi>abide in the Doctrine of Chriſt</hi> I do not equal all Quakers in this charge, but to all I ſay, Read, and conſider your ways, <hi>Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4.16. A wiſe man feareth and departeth from evil, but the Fool rageth and is confident: See alſo <hi>v.</hi> 6, 12, 14, 15, 17, 22, 25, 27, 33.</p>
            <p>Secondly; if perchance ye will not read, not hear, others will: wherefore them I invite to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, from this our Narrative,</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:48750:24"/>
            <p n="1">1. That Primitive Quakers were very trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to Magiſtrates and Miniſters with their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Meſſages from the Lord. They would come and openly diſturb Mr. <hi>Gilpin</hi> (and hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds more) in the Church, and <hi>H. W.</hi> in his houſe, and the Juſtices in theirs. Such was the temper and tendency of the Quakers Spirit, they could not ſtay at home in their callings, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6. to 15. They were immediately car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried againſt Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, the two ſo great Ordinances of God for governing and bleſſing the World; but what's the matter that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſo ſeldom hear of their Meſſages now adays to Magiſtrates and Miniſters? Why none to Long <hi>William</hi> and his Parliament, as to <hi>Oliver</hi> and his? They can tell a pretty reaſon or two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at we may ask, is their Spirit ceaſed, or are they weary (O <hi>utinam!</hi>) with ſeeing their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies ſo oft baffled and diſappointed? had they not need aſſure the Magiſtrate, that now their Mind is changed? Elſe how unſecure is the State and Church? Whom may they not accuſe at this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ate? And inſtigate others (for herein the Pope <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d they agree) to execute their <hi>Anathema's?</hi> Mark the Peaceable mind, and Innocence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſighting, unſwearing Quakers: Others they'll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pley to ſwear, at every Cuſtom-houſe, that is, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> damn'd to do their drudgery.</hi> And <hi>G. K</hi>'s caſe done ſufficiently ſhews the World their benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to any they diſlike. See 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.10, 12, 15. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 27.14. Wrath is cruel, and Anger is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gious, and who can ſtand before Envy?</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Scripture and Quakeriſm are mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al enemies; <hi>H. W.</hi> muſt forſake that, if he'l turn Quaker, Turk, or Papiſt; none of their Meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to him are from that. Indeed they boldly
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48750:25"/>Ape its Language, as the Devil uſes to do in his Oracles. But if Scripture is ſuch <hi>Serpent's meat,</hi> ſuch a Lying Book, or is not (as it affirms it ſelf to be) the <hi>very Word of God,</hi> why doth the pretended Spirit of God in Quakers aim to ſpeak ſo like it? uſe its Phraſes, and way of delivering its reports? Doth the Holy Spirit or does Jeſus Chriſt love to reſemble and imitate falſe ſeducing Authors? as the Pen-men of the Bible are, if they be not ſuch as they own themſelves to be: But if indeed they were ſent and taught of God, then is Quakeriſm con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine that is of God. I know what reſpect they give it, ſince a good Act of Parliament taught them what to ſay for peace but how elſe do they yet honour it? And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they do, what ſort of Chriſtians can they be? The Jews were to retain and obſerve <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.4. and we Chriſt's, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> I find thoſe called, who receive Chriſt's and his Apoſtles Doctrine about the Perſon and Office of Chriſt who died for Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: <hi>Acts.</hi> 11.26. with <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.21. But they do not: Nay, you hear them count thoſe go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtians that heard not this Doctrine; but who <hi>Believers</hi> can ſuch be? <hi>Ro.</hi> 10.14. Do they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hereby confeſs another Chriſt? <hi>Ro.</hi> 16.20, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Well, though they be Enemies to Scripture, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them the Scriptures of both Teſtaments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fulfilled, that ſuch <hi>deceivers will come,</hi> Matthew 24. and that there is a Spirit of Error as well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Truth; <hi>many ſmall Antichriſts</hi> as one Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> one; ſo that we need not call in queſtion o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Scripture-Chriſtianity for them; nay, they affo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> us an argument that it is the very Word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Words of God.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:48750:25"/>
            <p n="3">3. Obſerve the pride and danger of caſting off Scripture-Rule. Honeſt Men come to the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Light to be tried and undeceived; theſe run from it, that none may have whereby to convince them, admitting no appeal but to their own Light, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Defendant will be his own Judge: This holds them faſt in the Devil's ſnare. And how credulous can they be of any Reports! I know whom they ſurmiſed to be the Author of a Book that offended them, and Anſwered it is his, with many lying, ſcurrilous Reflections, when he knew no more of its Author than they: But that's a ſmall thing. Mark how this Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Revelation began, even <hi>at her FEET,</hi> to make ſure of entire poſſeſſion; no wonder they count all others <hi>carnal,</hi> ſince Quakers are <hi>all over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Spiritual,</hi> that they can receive ſpiritual Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions and Divine Revelations, even in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eels; but hear the conſequence, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.3, 5. 6, 8, 9. and <hi>v.</hi> 17. to 23. I have ſometime heard of Monkiſh Diſpoſſeſſions, and egreſſe of Demons <hi>à poſteriori,</hi> but never of any illapſe of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit like this. <hi>Riſum teneatis?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. How buſy the Devil hath been, is, and will be againſt the Word and Spirit of Chriſt, and thereby againſt his Church and Honour; and ah! how ſtrong his deluſions when once ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted? Hardly were any of theſe ſeduced Wretches wrought to the leaſt meaſure of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and ſhame, after moſt woful fruſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Dreams, and publick detection of their Lies. This is the fruit of caſting off Scripture, Miniſtry and Ordinances as outward, carnal things; ſo eaſy it is to retain a pretence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion quite ſeparate from its life, truth and power. Here we have great ſwelling names of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:48750:26"/>
               <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Revelation,</hi> and of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> but coupled with a fierce bloody Zeal as any in Popery Might not ſuch Revelation be as good a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to Poiſon or Stab <hi>H. W.</hi> as to put the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate upon hanging him on ſuch proof? Reader, theſe are no new things in the World Marvell not if the Devil acts now as he did of old. But what a ſenſleſs ſhamm is Quaker pretence to <hi>Univerſal Charity?</hi> Sometimes they tell us that even <hi>Socrates</hi> is ſafe in obeying his Light, as <hi>T. S.</hi> of late; why then do they not let all alone to be taught by their own Light? But their treatment of <hi>H. W.</hi> when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd, ſhews that they can endure none but themſelves. And here obſerve their ſingular Charity to Proteſtants, whom they ſet on even grounds with Papiſts, Jews, Turks and Pagans juſt ſo and no more. A goodly price is this put on Reformed Religion! and the glorious ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel! ſince Pagans be and do as well without it. But ſays the Spirit of Truth ſo is <hi>Pſa.</hi> 147.19, 20. <hi>John</hi> 14.6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18. and are not we highly obliged by this their Candor? Oh the front of theſe Men! Truly did we uſe Scripture no more in our houſes and Aſſemblies than moſt Quakers do in theirs, as well we might be Pagans.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Mark by what means <hi>H. W.</hi> once a Quaker, eſcapes out of their Net. In him you firſt ſee there may be fearful long Backſlidings of good people, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37.23, 24, to 34. whom yet effectual Grace will recover, as <hi>Peter. Satan</hi> though he winnow them, ſhall loſe his prey. Were it poſſible, he would deceive the very Elect, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.24. But Chriſt hath prayed <hi>that their Faith do not utterly, finally fail:</hi> Wiſe and merciful
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48750:26"/>proviſion hath he made in the new Covenant for ſuch Caſes, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.4, 5. But ſee here by what Methods and Arguings he was ſet right, and reduced to Truth; 'twas <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> juſt uſe of his Reaſon, and conſideration gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Scripture, that repreſented Quakeriſm to him groundleſs, abſurd and Impious; then durſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e no longer abide in it: May others give like Glory to free, rich and powerful Grace, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.63. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. coming out from among Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers.</p>
            <p n="6">6. How wiſe and faithful is the Lord in exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing his Children by Perſecutions, Afflictions, Reproaches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.67, 71, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for much endeavour had been uſed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ince <hi>H. W.</hi> and his Wife, of that Error; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather than let them ſin unto death, God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>its their own neareſt Relations to be their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urpeſt ſcourge; this opened their eyes to let them ſee the ſtrong Deluſions of the Quaking ſpirit, and now they humble themſelves great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; write an Acknowledgment of their Errour; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eg Prayer of the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and after a while, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere received. Reader, ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 94.12, 13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.78, 79, 80. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.10, 11. wherein the Lord fully declares his fatherly purpoſes in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting his Children, eſpecially in caſe they go <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ay. But it's dreadful when Corrections make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o impreſſion, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.3. Thus it hath been with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt of <hi>H. W's</hi> perſecutors to this day; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ning which frame of Spirit I wiſh others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y take warning from <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.10, 15, 16, 17, 19 — <hi>cap.</hi> 8.5, 6, 12.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:48750:27"/>
            <p n="7">7. Think what need of thy Compaſſions and Prayer for theſe ſo deluded, that by the Goſpel they may be better enlightned, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. <hi>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 3.18. The Lord is patient, (Oh how patient! towards them, ſuffering his Name to be thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> blaſphemed. The day is not yet come (but it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> coming, <hi>Jude</hi> 14, 15.) wherein he will judge th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> World by the Lord Jeſus Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, whom he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ordained Judge of the Quick and Dead. Whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he thus forbears, it's meet we ſhould act in a li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Spirit towards ſinners. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10, 11. <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24, 25. even towards theſe; they are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alike deplorable. God once convinced many ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate <hi>Jews,</hi> and will more; ſo he recover'd ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from the depths of Popery: Nor are all Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers equal in ſin. Some ground of charitable hope remains, that if they durſt examine, the Veil might be rent from their blinded minds. I know their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3, 4. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13. but <hi>H. W.</hi> and others, after many Years deluſion were recovered Who then dares ſay that no more ſhall, after a longer ſtay in their Tents? They muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked ſharply; yet, Chriſtian Reader, put on Bowels of large Compaſſions: Charity for thee they have none, till thou turn Quaker; no, not common Pocket-charity, moſt of them confine that to their own; thou therefore put on the more Charity to them, as Chriſt Jeſus to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, murdering <hi>Jews.</hi> It's hard to ſay what thou canſt do to convince or gain any of them If they will not hear thee, nor the Church, they muſt be left to God. But <hi>Noah,</hi> that perfect Man, and preacher of Righteouſneſs, condemned the World. That thou mayſt profit them, or at leaſt Antidote thy ſelf, I beſeech thee,</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:48750:27"/>
            <p n="1">1. To practiſe in the name of Chriſt that Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of Luſts and Paſſions they pretend to; particularly that of Self conceit, Revenge, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y Zeal: Theſe thou ſeeſt our Perfectioniſts had not put off. St. <hi>John</hi> in his day, to ſecure againſt worldly Anti-Chriſts then appearing, adviſed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rucify worldly Affections, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.15. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.5, 6. ſo ſay I: Love of Gain hath made many Quakers; for the Devil, and the worſt of Men will be kind to their own.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Adorn Chriſtian Doctrine (which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs not) in a holy, ſhining life: Be better than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. Do they make ſhew of any Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, or laudable practice? It's a vile ſhame if Chriſt's Diſciples out-do them not, whoſe Light, Principles and aſſiſting Grace ſo far exceed theirs. They once made a ſpecious ſhew of Humility, Self-Denial, Contempt of the World, plain, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Dealing, frugality and gravity in Apparel: The World ſees it's not ſo now; their Rule can ſtretch and bend, but thine is not ſo ſlippery and novable: Let them ſee, that better Principles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ake better Men; eſpecially beware of caſting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y Offence before them to confirm them in their way.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Keep Humble and low in thine own eyes; There is no cauſe that ſinful man ſhould lean to his own wiſdom, ſtrength, or Righteouſneſs. God reſiſteth the proud that will not bow to, and depend on his Guidance and Grace; but his Favour he ſhews to the Humble, ſuch he guides, leaving others to be miſguided by their own luſts. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.11, 12.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:48750:28"/>
            <p n="4">4. Magnify Jeſus Chriſt the incarnate Son o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, the great Light, and Saviour of the World<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as neceſſary to thee in all thy Affairs with God and with thy Spiritual Enemies, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.31 <hi>Col.</hi> 2.3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. He is precious to ſuch as know him, or themſelves, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7, 8. The Faithful cleave to, and follow him in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his Ways and Ordinances; by Faith in him they live and are preſerved. Ah! Reader, beware o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them that vilify him, and his Wiſdom; Beware of the Quaker's Spirit and Inſinuations. It has oft appeared that ſuch as have joined themſelves to them, are prepared for any Deluſions the Devil can ſuggeſt; their caſe is mournful, but they ſcorn our pity. It's diſmal to think how ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom any of them are reclaimed, and how Pagan like their young Generation is educated; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that this ſhould be at this day in a Reformed, Evangelized Nation is ſaddeſt of all.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Grieve not the Holy Spirit of Truth. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> where wilt thou run when he ceaſes to lead thee Dare not to diſobey that Light he conveys by and from the Oracles of God. Receive Heavenly Doctrine, even the whole counſel of God in the Love of it, leſt thou be delivered to believe lies, and hardened through the deceitfulneſs of Sin Of all people, proud, empty Profeſſor, whoſe ears are itching, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ikeſt to be the Seducer's Prey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for this I dare appear to all that mind their laſe Proſelytes. When many deceivers were abroad, St. <hi>John</hi> thought it needful more fully to inſtruct and confirm his Diſciples in preſent Fundamental Truth, which thoſe and ours agree to ſubvert. See 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.18. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo went about confirming the Diſciples ſouls, Acts 14.21, 22, 23.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48750:28"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. in the Doctrine they had received, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. hold that faſt, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2 14, 15. <hi>Jude</hi> 3.— 17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.24, 25. Surely theſe cautionary ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onition; are of uſe ſtill, and ought to be alike <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cceptable to thee.</p>
            <p>Finally, Dread the Methods whereby others are inveigled, <hi>i. e. a pretence of all inward Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ulity in Religion.</hi> A form of Godlineſs without life and Spirit God abhorrs; but while we are in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e Body, we muſt employ Souls and bodies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his worſhip, we muſt have viſible, ſenſible ordinances; ſuch the Wiſdom of God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inted us: But theſe waxing ſecure and wanton <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> formal profeſſion, firſt caſt off all ordinances, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> outward duties, all prayer, only with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erve, when their own Spirits would give 'em <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> jogg, <hi>i. e.</hi> when their fleſh had nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o object. Thou therefore when tempted to quit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he beaten path of Scripture-worſhip, be ſure to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee good and clear divine Warrant for any new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny commended to thee. So thou hadſt need, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho muſt render to God an account why thou doſt turn aſide from the great Shepherd's ſents. Wiſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> in <hi>Proverbs</hi> 2.20. coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ls thee to walk in the way of good men, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eep the paths of the Righteous: So <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. do you ſo, praying all along to be taught of God, and led by his Spirit into all Truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> means of his Word. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.18. Open thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ine eyes, that I may ſee wondrous things out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f thy Law. <hi>v.</hi> 19. I am a ſtranger in the Earth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ide not thy Commandments from me. <hi>v.</hi> 24. Thy Teſtimonies alſo are my delight, and my Counſellors.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:48750:29"/>
            <head>THE CONCLUSION TO THE <hi>Sober-minded Quakers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ONce more I beſeech you hear what this ſtory ſpeaks to you: You plainly ſee the native tendency of your pretended Revelation yet all your Speakers to this day hold faſt the pretence, alledging they know not who ſhall ſpeak untill <hi>the Spirit moves</hi> in that very hour of that aſſembly; nor what ſhall be ſpoken: A conceit that has oft made me ſmile; when I have been told a week beforehand by your ſelves, that ſuch a man will on ſuch a day ſpeak at ſuch a place, but <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> populum phaleras,</hi> the credulous Mob muſt ſtill be fed with wonders, and the Women too, (who of all things love to have their Tongues at liberty) muſt be heard gagling as the green <hi>Apron</hi> gives them utterance: Of this I know ſome of you are ſick and weary, though they dare not openly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn it, ſince ſo many have undertaken to juſtify that impudent contradiction to the God of Order, and to baffle thoſe 2 plain texts. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.34, 35. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11, 12. But in truth the woful miſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures of our 3 ſhe-Apoſtles, not to mention the fulſom noiſe and nonſence of ſuch others, may well turn your ſtomachs againſt that principle
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:48750:29"/>which has Jet the Female Spirit looſe: How to get <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of this unruly Evil by your notion, I cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ern: Therefore I adjure you, ſeriouſly conſider <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at you have done in caſting off Scripture-rule, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ucking up that hedge, chuſing to walk in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er light: Some of your Crafts-men, I know, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> now deny this, whoſe Ingenuity I cannot but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ire, ſince the Fact is notorious in 1 00 of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and in conſtant practice; for God's Book <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> no place or honour in your Aſſemblies, nor do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Teachers ſubmit themſelves or Doctrine to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Judge. From this you cannot honourably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, without taking ſhame to your ſelves, as ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e Penitents uſe to do; and proclaiming to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that herein was your firſt and moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s Error: If yet you ſee it an Error, 'tis a fatal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, Why then will you not confeſs and forſake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.176. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.27. Erring is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on to Men, and why not to you? 'Tis an old, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d common Error, and harder to correct, but the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> neceſſary, ſince you can elſe never know therein to return. The Scripture is God's own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oviſion, to prevent or recover from Deluſions: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you will not yet appear before that Tribunal, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nk you cover your Sins, and cannot proſper: come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th therefore from the tents of Deiſts and Papiſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all that ſhun <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eavenly light; and if you mean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eſtly; let us ſee you henceforth teach and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ip, and walk by this holy Rule. Search the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e Records, which are able to make you wiſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>hation through faith in Chriſt Jeſus. You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do leſs, if you have due care of Immortal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouls; it's utterly unſafe to continue under other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ance: Reſolve but on a little honeſt humility, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d you may eſcape the ſnare of the proud Devil, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rying as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 119.10, 11.18, 19.33 to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and God may yet grant you Repentance to the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:48750:30"/>acknowledgment of the Truth: Your Spirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> grown evidently tame and towardly in other thing it keeps exact time in your Meetings by virtue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a watch <hi>within you,</hi> for an <hi>outward clock,</hi> or Gla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> on a high place is an abomination: Why the may it not allow you to alter in this, which is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> very foundation of all you do amiſs? Cloſe n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now your Eyes to this warning, for fear of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Condemnation in <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.18, 19. <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.41. What adviſe you is juſt and fair: Which if you will n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hear, it only remains, that (as the good old Proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Jeremy</hi>) my Soul weep in ſecret over your inco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigibleneſs, and that you reap. the bitter fruits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your obſtinacy, as the very true and faithful Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Son of God, has denounced in <hi>Luke</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:48750:30"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>John Harris</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> in <hi>Little Britain.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Revelation unvail'd: Or, an Eſſay towards the Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, 1. When many Scripture Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hecies had their accompliſhment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd turned Hiſtory, 2. What are fulfilling, 3. What reſt ſtill to be fulfilled; with a Gueſs at the time of them. With an Appendix, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing that <hi>Pagan Rome</hi> was not <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en,</hi> Rev. 17. <hi>And that the Jews ſhall be converted.</hi> By <hi>Samuel Petto,</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Sudbury</hi> in <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk,</hi> price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Faithful Narrative of the Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful and Extraordinary Fits which Mr. <hi>Tho. Spatchet</hi> (late of <hi>Dunwich</hi> and <hi>Cookly</hi>) was under by Witchcraft: Or, a Myſterious Providence in his even Unparallel'd Fits. With an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb facs="tcp:48750:31"/>of his firſt Falling into, Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour under, and (in part) delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out of them. Wherein are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral remarkable Inſtances of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Effects of fervent Prayer. The whole drawn up and written by <hi>Same Petto,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> who was an Eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a great part. With a Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Preface, price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mathematical Divinity: Or, a plain demonſtration from the Holy Scriptures, that the times of this work were fore-appointed by the Covenant made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and determined to be according to the meaſure of the Age and fulneſs of Chriſt. Kept ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſince the World began, but i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now made plain upon 12 Tables in a Solar Calendar, as familiar to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding as any common Almanack. With a full proof that this is the laſt Generation which ſhall not paſs away till all things be fulfilled, and the Gates of Righteouſneſs be opened, being the reſult of many years ſtudy. By <hi>Elias Palmer,</hi> price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:48750:31"/>
            <p>A compendious Hiſtory of the firſt Inventers and Inſtitutors of the moſt famous Arts, Myſteries, Laws, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms and Manners in the whole World. Together with many other Ratities and Remarkable things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to which are added ſeveral curious Inventions, peculiarly attributed to <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Engliſhmen.</hi> The whole Alphabetically digeſted, and very helpful to the reading of Hiſtory, price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A new method of Educating Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: Or, Rules and Directions for the well ordering and governing them during their younger Years. Shewing that they are capable at the Age of three years to be cauſed to learn Languages, and moſt Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; which if obſerv'd by Parents, would be of greater value than a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds portion. Alſo what me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods are to be uſed by Breeding Women; and what diet is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for them and their Children, to prevent Wind, Vapours, Convulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:48750:32"/>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Written (to diſengage the World from thoſe ill cuſtoms in Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, it has been ſo long uſed to) by <hi>Tho. Trion,</hi> Author of the way to Health, Long Life and Happineſs, price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſhort Diſcourſe of the Riſe, Nature and Management of the Small Pox, and all putrid Fevers, occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by the Death of our late in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Queen. Together with a Philoſophical Account of an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Remedy for theſe and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſeaſes. By <hi>T. Byfield</hi> M. D. price 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medicina Practica:</hi> Or, Practical Phyſick; ſhewing the method of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the moſt uſual Diſeaſes happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Humane Bodies, with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the <hi>Praecipiolum,</hi> or uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Medicine of <hi>Paracelſus;</hi> to which is added, the Philoſophick Works of <hi>Hermes Triſmegiſtus, Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Perſicus, Geber Arabs, Arteſius Longavus, Nicholas Flammel, Roger
<pb facs="tcp:48750:32"/>Bachon,</hi> and <hi>George Ripley,</hi> all Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated out of the beſt Latin Editions, into <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Together with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Comment upon the firſt Book of <hi>Hermes,</hi> the moſt Ancient of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers. The whole compleated in three Book. By <hi>William Salmon</hi> Profeſſor of Phyſick, price 5 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Angliae Metropolis:</hi> Or, the preſent State of <hi>London;</hi> with Memorials comprehending a full and ſuccinct account of the Ancient and Modern State thereof. Its Original, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Rights, Liberties, Charters, Trade, Cuſtoms, Priviledges, and other Remarkables, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> firſt Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the late ingenious <hi>Tho. de laun,</hi> Gent. and continued by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Balm of the Covenant ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the Bleeding Wounds of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Saints; firſt compoſed for the relief of a pious and worthy Family, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ourning over the Deaths of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>opeful Children, and now made
<pb facs="tcp:48750:33"/>publick for the ſupport of all Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſorrowing on the ſame or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other account; to which is added. Sermon Preached for the Funeral that Excellent and Religious Gent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>John Upton</hi> of <hi>Lupton,</hi> Eſq; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>John Flavel,</hi> late Miniſter of the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel at <hi>Dartmouth</hi> in <hi>Devon.</hi> price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
